Worse year ad
...twenty fifteen addition I'm here with some good friends
we've known each other for years so this is almost like a little-bitty slumber party for us
Was...start.
...alzheimer's...samoa.
So, what do you guys do for microsoft gosh, what don't we do the...we
are around everything on janitorial judge editorials so, no,
we I work on...see sharply we work on the csharp team
I focused primarily on id experiences so
editing experiences things like intelligence for csharp for visual...that sort of thing and
user I focus...language so I believe the language sign efforts so
the language itself that we all know and love...part of your work it is my life and blog nice
so for a while how to type without me it's right...love we love everybody
...lifeblood if we have...fighting right now no I'm better so what's...
...and up so let's start with this what...with you guys
...so the first question is what is roslyn and what does it do that
...asked me back there to aspect so well,
roslyn is a is a project that?
It took more than a tenth of my lifespan are you still think about the pillow fight is that with
messing you up it's a little distract right okay so,
note roslyn is a project we started about six years ago kind of reboot
of several projects before that so it's the desire to have something like of has been there for many years right but,
it was basically a rebuilding of the entire csharp language stack really
from the ground-up starting with compiler rebuilding up to compiler building api on top of it
so that you could basically introspective or generate source code or do things
...to write things against the compiler all the information in the compiler about your source code to
write smart tools right or do smart things with source code and,
then on top of that building other pieces of that stack so the id
...doing things like in exploring
...replica experience scripting there's a lot of things that one-in-two project
a project arousal so for ten I don't know anything done that was really fast so, no,
...within...figures...
Know what kind of schooling could you build that wooded subjected
to the compiler what are some things that you see that people have
started going well...things like style cup from.
...check various parts of your code and highlighted in the id and offer your fixes to
changer code...whatever are things that anybody can write and inject into the compile and have
a light up in the id refactoring stuff like that you can I think that we're already
starting to see the take up on is writing things and tamaras
...analyzers and fixes on top of roslyn and shipping them with your libraries to help you
...in the right...so, we can imagine api not just coming with xml comments
...and guidelines but actually actionable executable
...if you...so are you injecting into the...pipeline or what's
...in...ours...yes I mean so?
In particular the analyzer framework which is there's a particular api
...the supported way to basically perform analysis what
is inside the compiler actually runs yes during the
...compilers and its various stages of the times when it's binding the
that the file to get all the semantic information that's when it's also calling into the analyzer to
produce additional diagnostic so what what's really cool about it is that you can write
...analyzer to...either notify the user about something and for some sort
of semantic that probably wouldn't be appropriate in the compiler itself got right it's in the
compiler things are certainly appropriate things like broken syntax...you know,
this type isn't there that sort of thing that are perfectly appropriate...compiler but,
something like style cup,
for example, which might not be something would...about we've done a few of those in the past and
they always feel a little weird now we have a framework where we can go and add more diagnostics
...guidance for users without actually having to touch the compiler
...tyrannical manager that says curly brace on the next line every time, you
know, that's a sensible that so, yeah, but,
that's the right...update you could force it now using...so let's take a let's take a
...back step back and what does it actually look like to call into the
rosalyn api what is it that you're getting back and how...you use that information to do these kind of
Well, it's an.
It's an api it's an object model...so,...you typically do is you will makethis
is an project template that you used to build and analyzer and fixes for instance set up so the
...played around the core of the logic is.
The api will offer you an object model of source code...that you can then and
it's not just it's syntax tree...fully concrete syntax
...every little bit of information imacs...does semantic analysis
four-year-old binding else and you can ask questions about all those things traverses model
do whatever you want and once you figured out that I want to squiggles here so on you
can build a fixture that will take the code around that place
and transform it for the user if they choose to activate the fix...that
...in the id so you always just operating on an object...the analyzer framework
the code aware libraries and...of thing is it's a it's a key
kind of usage that we're envisioning really going after in visual
...to your twenty fifteen it's actually with the rc that was released today
...effectively go live for us go right analyzers
...but...is there's so much more you can do...just one aspect one
vision we have no this is we're going to attack this time around there's a lot of other stuff that we're looking at
...I don't think I think people realize effectively
rewriting the compiler is like taking the bottom out of a house.
Putting the bottom in putting it back on hoping everything works if you guys have a lot of like
...gauss's working well it's exactly like that and if I can push the metaphor super far
...xr you can imagine I always
do it's like it's almost as if that foundation even had imperfections that if you didn't include
...imperfections again the whole house would still fall down right you
...really try and replicate exactly the behavior the compiler because
backward compatibility is important of a very important...there's a lot of legacy code out
there's a lot of existing projects that are in production and we can't we can't afford to break any of
that so here's a question it sounds like you're actually getting a estes back with semantic analysis we're
calling the eight guys doesn't this slow stuff down a little bit...you guys doing to make the speed
...so the this is something that I don't think you see in a lot of places
is a super efficient implementation of
the language semantics but in such a way that is both.
Efficient when doing batch compilation like pipeline through generating coded the other
...also fission for incremental usage rags the id asks
...all the time a it's an efficient and useful even when the
code is broken because when you in id codes broken most the time...
when I'm writing code on this broken all the time...and riza dot you can...not...
roslyn but also in order to in order to we'd made some you
could say modern aren't a...traditional choices in about what how the api
words whenever the source code changes you essentially
get a completely new syntax feedback completely generated from scratch
...think it's a new object these trees are immutable and what really do is do a lot of sharing under the
hood and some the incremental...parsing some
caching some lazy stuff so that every time a single characters type
...deleted we are effectively observable computing
...new syntax tree for your from the ground-up except we use all these techniques behind...to make
it super efficient and that means that having
...object model means that is super safe for
someone to consume they know that somebody else is not going to change it under the hood or change
...there under their feet while they're working on it because it can't change right and, it means
...we can paralyze a lot of things so we can make full use of the increasing number of cpu
...that would be available well that's really close so I love the way that
...saying these things are returning estes
...state it seems I would be contrary to the thought of what if I want to make a change
...make a copy...back yes as a single think of it this a single mutable
bearable and the whole system and that is the root of everything that's cool so you generate a new thing from the
old thing also when you microcode transformations right you the way that you
transformer syntax trees to build a new one from the pieces of the old one got yank it
back again you can even
...and this really happens like...when you use the id you can see this happening before you
yank...to be the new state of the world the thing that's in the buffer you
...and preview so you have this is what the current world looks like...a preview went on
...business live this is the future we didn't even run the analyses on top of it
...in there and say by the way this that would be a problem here if you this is going to future
early brace on the next one I mean that's what we're going to
...in that case there would be...google that would show up...because what we do is we just
...the id features simply run on it's on and on a snapshot of that object
...right so if we have a future speculative
kind of snapshot the id features still function on that so you know,
...this fix as a using will in the preview going to see the type colorized because it
is correct now...that's awesome so we'll take some questions here dusted, you know,
I have to ask with scripting interactive windows coming to
...fifty my god...space...it's been tempt down...
Has every right I feel so much where I almost feel like I don't have to...globe?
it's been a big year for us last year when we were sitting up here you know, we
had just had a historic moment a couple days before we released rousing open-source on
...the compiler...cheering on the...there was, yeah,...there was like, yeah,
so, sense then, you know, we moved to get hub and at right after moving to get her
because...were just not...had lots of spare
...we also opened up the rest of the stack and we
...opened up the interactive window and scripting...so that stuff is actually
there can be in fact built so,
on visual studio so that and then we started openly talking about roadmap there ok so upon...get
...repo there is a road map for interactive in scripting I can't tell you when it'll
happen and you know, we're still wrapping up current version visual studio but,
it is hot off of off of that to get to the next thing so it's definitely
it's definitely still on the roadmap and I was actually thinking about showing it on friday and our talkyeah,
just a...slow we have a talk on friday you know, maybe show it your bombs are going to show up
obviously...maybe hopefully more people will
...right so next question what I didn't get clear about roslyn is it
is it compiling still to il...binary it compiles to I'll just like
the old compiler ...happily handy...over to dot net native which is
...happy to compile it down to binary so those are two separate things...those
...lies...different sort of...of the whole thing it's just I mean it when you think about the
compilation piece...you're nothing about the api it's almost just a wholesale can replacement of the existing
...the same...right so compiling to I'll definitely what you...compiler to do
...it will generate more efficient I'll that's different okay...that's awesome so let's
get into this next topic which I think is interesting roslyn has been open-source
...open or open-source...contribution...process
for that have there been contributions to talk about that?
Yeah, that's.
That's all we've got for today you know, it's been.
A year now since we first went complex
...to get hub but it's been a year of
processing learning and we've been developing in the open and, we've had some missteps along the way the
communities call this out appropriately along the way and, we made some corrections so,
now I mean we...we're taking contributions...substantial things happening where people are
making contributions and it's also kind of hand-in-hand with our with our friends
...you know, core effects and brush you'll are also taking broad contributions
...just over the last year of experimentation learning how to kinda
live in this world and, also figure out how we can take contributions into the product
and all those kinds of things we've learned a lot so, yet please so many more questions
...adding polar...as you say what kind of stuff...people.
But, first...like xml dot comment...arrives anti-virus
...be the first one to stews amenable regressing everyplace eight-inch with
...been actually there
...very interesting poorer...to the vb compiler we take bug fixes in the id
...there's all sorts of we actually have we have an up for grabs label anybody can go grab before if it's something that,
you know, yes, we should fix that we don't...outright throw the bug away,...
but, it's...be in this released...we get a lot of really high-priority things but you
want help out feel free and, they've been a number of little bug fixes and tweaks
...pretty cool another place we get contribution those not just, you know,
contributing code but also contributing to the cut to the discussion the conversation right having
our issues open you can talk about if you want csharp languages on the open...beyond that that's the next thing
...the language design so that's a good segue into service this guassian
...like...do see that...going let's move on to talk about the next
version of csharp yes the one that's coming up with csharp six right so you have six
is coming out yes and what is it that we get there that we don't have before what we would
have been doing well you get more language features of
...language and the csharp six
it's sort of really like it's a celebration of our new agility with their with
a new code base...code base that we can do a lot of little
...very useful things that were just too hard to do for their value
in the old kobe's really took
it will really took a round of these are things that will make my code simpler get rid of
...of...played this beautiful little things that will also be showing and I'll talk on friday okay
...that are just I wholesale going to change?
How you...how we write csharp like every little piece of csharp code is going to be
different if people use these features but in small...okay that's sort
of the so what are what are some of those small changes that are going to make our
...better...get only autumn props string interpolation and
name a feature that allows you to safely get the string for a value
...in the program that'll
...refactoring bugs there's the null conditional operator
...dot as a question dot that lets you check for...dotting into things rather than having to
...around everything so on all these little things...just
...things up that's awesome so let's take some questions now moving forward
to csharp so you can't believe what you were already talking about is we haven't even csharp
...artsy or what are the sm so now they're asmodeus
of seven the question is which of the abstract...features like paramagnetism...would you like to
...and...it almost seems like passive-aggressive like which
...features...csharp...right now well I think
...programmers including...they ask are here they will know that these features weren't
...first on whether there's there's a whole
lead tradition of functional languages these things come from and f sharp as an eml dialect fits in
with that well but we are very inspired by having...sharp is one of our system
languages and seeing the usage of it so it's true that in csharp seven
in particular...number of the features we've been looking at since january
reaping designing csharp seven and design...go out every week to
...sawdust to get up and everybody contributes
...to the discussion so on proposals their galore lots of discussion
...of those features have a functional slant to them and I think that's sort of
and we're still like totally just playing around figuring out what you
...should be about maybe it shouldn't even be called seven?
Maybe we should call it...sharps I mean that's the that's an
...always it as I should go on there and do discussions we I think you should submit
...what you take the temperature of community and right ...of the
seems that I think we're kind of focusing in on is it has to be easier to work with
wired data so, there's some things were looking at
their various other functional style writings we're talking about like
...and they mention and, in their question also?
What did they mention it went about...discriminated audience matches stuff like that would definitely
look at that another thing that we've been spending the last month so training on is trying to?
...sort of retroactively make csharp null aware
of in the sense that we can help you write code that doesn't have...reference except
...a big and which is almost impossible to do is an existing language and
top of a runtime everything has a default value that's null but, we're the default value like to
...gas exactly much better right world
...solve this for you guys...mandel problem ogg?
On...to get have discussion and put that...good to...okay,
so, with...the next question you guys
are developing csharp seven in the open so the design nodes that you
...you sit down and type is up as you talk about these are online...now so
how can someone go on there and sort of voice their opinion and people been doing
...comment they,... the...they say...rice but...you know,
sometimes the issues don't get a lot of discussion your regular issues but when
...post...he's a rock star everybody
...everybody's...that...to...sanction everybody's
links design jan so you get you get lots of opinions and?
What surprised me going to give especially which is a large community is?
I shouldn't say...surprised me but it did the quality of the feedback
is just amazing man, yeah, it's really it's so really get in the
habit because of that really get habit of circling back looking at what people said since last time and,
taking that in as part of the discussion so the feedback loop even now we're not even building anything or we
...decided anything yet feedback loop is already so awesome that is really helping us...
the feature forward focus on what's important cut the stuff that's not important get the right direction that's great well
hazing let's...are questions here a lot of the top of the
...csharp seven work list
...influence by functional programming how far with the csharp
...willing to go in that direction, you know, it feels like.
Like there's good things and all languages but it feels like you can't really make a language be all things to
all people version you draw the line I think for us it's very important
that csharp retains...
It has to keep feeling like csharp it's okay
for to evolve we shouldn't have a revolution
where changes it's feeling completely and we also don't want to end up in a situation where
...like two camps that can both coexist in the language of
two fundamentally different ways of doing things and right sort of a dual set of
features for each so we have to keep the unity of the language somehow and that means that even though
we're very strongly inspired by some functional features for instance right we keep
...on them until they feel like they fit and...that they that
...are writing natural for csharp programmer and if we can't do that we're not going to put... the
cool thing is that when you say it feels right and...you don't just mean you...mean the people
...giving also feedback absolute...absolute ok however the people don't give feedback, you know,
we can now...right is it possible to create code analyzers that in fact
and rewrite code before it goes to later stages at the moment no,
that's not possible not in the sense of writing and analyzer what you can do is set feels more like a treads
...that I mean you can their things they're tricks you could do the tricks...play I would say it's I
was not possible it's possible it would be a lot of work eight-year now you're,
you're in the realm of...somehow insert myself...the admissible pipeline ramon task transference
...code before it goes to the...the actual compilers stage and, you know,
make my changes than before they actually get...the about and people have done
those sorts of things that one of the things people have done it for ...certain ways to do it, you know,
if a opie weaving is one that people talk about lot-a and also doing language featuresI've seen
I've seen you'll for each is and all sorts of different language features that are done that way one of the
key problems you run into is that you don't get tooling support for right
so things don't highlighting the editor,
you know, you don't you don't get intelligence writer you might just have squiggles because
the compiler that's in the id e that's loaded inside of visual studio another one that's wrong it's actually, you know,
compiling on the command line of...things are...so that's a that's a problem
the so at the moment it's hard I would say it's just hard...was very
...beauty of visual studios...gives us like a lot of stuff to work with an roslyn sort of
a support service to give you that extra stuff so I would you want kinda go against the grain
...you know, the door's not close on that it's just the one-man
...get out there and...right so next what do you think the chance of
...fixed arrays of not atomic types in the language?
Well, that's very specific is very specific to explain that questionmaybe without
remember pretending I don't know any...don't fix the... arrays that are.
Laid out in lima memory and, concurrently that's and, unsafe feature only works with
a very few types we could certainly look at doing that I want to say that sort of strikes
...theme.
Of features that would help...
And, that's one of the things that I feel we can also make some headway with
...seven to go for places where
it things are unnecessarily.
On performance about unnecessarily inefficient if we could do at...make
...better right and some a again you can go and...have...look at some of the things we thought about some of
them unfortunately require clr support again so that's a bigger discussion can we actually
ball il and what happens to people don't have access to the new version violence on
that so as soon as they charge we need to clr in on this right it's a bigger discussion
but that doesn't mean we can have it...it also makes...complicate the question because we're complex
right as well because today with...of six you can still down target, you know,
to...on a platform there's no sealer support required in fact that the very fact
made us actually cut a particular feature because if there is inconsistency and how it
works on lower versions of the see large so because we are requiring serialized
...preferred so that we can continue to continue target...a to
...with question dot...so?
All right so next will you...translator among languages I don't
thinkI don't know what they mean by that is that all a they mean take some
...source code and turn it into vb source...pilot and,
it can totally be done with...prototype the result...parcells but we didn't we didn't build them to be
bullet-proof features we built them for...because we build...csharp...so they're getting a
st...you could take that a...diverted to something you can actually, yeah,...a reorder
and but, you know, that or rather...visitor and that visitor just, you know,
build-up of each...it's complicated but you know,
you could...a little it's a little harder to types...too because to and from types
...because the...could also has a nice object model but of course that's all
...types group yom so for us to interrupt with that as we as we build that
...feature would be a little more work but a for
...because someone was just asking me about it today I think it would make a lot of sense for
...have something that would look at the look
...bb types and generate types...types for it and,
you...so use a back-end...have fun exercise to learn
...you would certainly learned really what it's not a super-human
feeding the something of the very cool process speaking of super-human
...flipper tasks many feature proposals
are for higher-level sugars lowered complex...our more system features such as
href locals...for csharp...let's explain the question first well-liked
electrodes...recover secondary clippers watching us right...I
...I did say speaking of super-human yes...that yes so.
System features and that sort of goes to the performance thing I
said again features that are targeting performance in fine-grain
manner a you could say that href locals for instance so that's...people know that
...parameters in csharp you can pass something by href like...for instance
...revenue copy it and,...be nice if...method also return
...to a struct and, it could and, you can store that in locals the as a
...so you to avoid copying that's where that's...feature and that is one that we
could probably do without as...changes in...sealer and I
think it's very likely that will do that...seven as part of that the push for low-hanging performance
...that's still different than the actual language that's more like on the compile-time kind of stuff
...that a language...the language thing it's a keyword href that you could add...of href zero
...goddess...and...my...the local declaration all right
so the question what's the status of destructive will heights.
Think...who chronic...you...
But, this is a charles
...style you show rule journalese yoman expressing ok so that's
...tights or a proposal for a way to
had types that automatically clean themselves up but the...there's a proposal out and
get up it's a little complex and because it also which is,
you know, admirable it also tries to track ownership of things so that you
don't clean them up twice and stuff like that and make sure...even if they handed off to someone else.
H the heart of the matter though is.
Having types that are the clean-up better than our
...disposable using story soif there's some way that we can enhance that make that better we can
...definitely talk to charles' about it or maybe...can come...get up maybe
...which...probably come up with something that fits more with the using feature
...language then what's out there current we've got only about a minute but there's another
super-human asking us questions I don
...are you planning to take videos of language design meetings like dot net core to
...recently we've been talking about I'm happy to...yeah,
record these we may we may get there yeah,
we have done it so far because we always end up saying things that united
...right like this is already bad enough right you try to
...the actually quite a few things and they turned out really final...that's I destroyed the recall is
...so final sixty seconds phoebe.
What you got to say about bb is something we still want to do is something that roslyn
...that we all happy roslyn support csharp and bb equally the
...parts of roslyn...bb and, yeah, it's really support and, there's even
...this even...far as
...api this...language agnostic model on...part of it so you can work with both
...at the same time so you get...a st?
From roslyn from bb dot echoed and csharp code you can do that it's a different a
estes obviously that renee's yes, yeah, that's a which we made...choices to make it high-fidelity with
...language so need to be different but subscribe there's there's you know,
some activity guys are contributing code and fixing compiler bugs and doing various things is
that it's kind of exciting what what's the...repost site that people can go look at the issues and
stuff so you have dot com slash dot net foundations of slash dot net slash
arousal also roslyn that io particular thank you so much for stopping by
thanks for watching and we'll see tomorrow with live content again the